<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon at the funeral of the reverend Mr. Thomas Grey, late Vicar of Dedham in Essex preach'd in the parish-church of Dedham, Febr. the 2d. 1691/2, with a short account of his life / by Joseph Powell ...</title>
            <author>Powell, Joseph, d. 1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55553</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3064</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3154</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11951430</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11951430</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51435</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55553)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51435)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 820:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon at the funeral of the reverend Mr. Thomas Grey, late Vicar of Dedham in Essex preach'd in the parish-church of Dedham, Febr. the 2d. 1691/2, with a short account of his life / by Joseph Powell ...</title>
                  <author>Powell, Joseph, d. 1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Speed ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>"Books printed for and sold by Thomas Speed, at the Three Crowns near the Royal Exchange in Cornhil, 1692." : p. [1] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gray, Thomas, d. 1692.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke II, 29 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51435:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51435:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON AT THE FUNERAL Of the Reverend Mr. <hi>THOMAS GREY,</hi> Late Vicar of <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex;</hi> PREACH'D In the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Dedham, Febr.</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> 1691/2.</p>
            <p>With a ſhort Account of his LIFE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSEPH POWELL,</hi> A. M. Rector of St. <hi>Mary on the Wall,</hi> in <hi>Colcheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Speed,</hi> at the <hi>Three Crowns</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:51435:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51435:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>St. LUKE CHAP. ii. VER. 29.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Lord now letteſt thou thy Servant depart in peace.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is related in the Sacred Hiſtory,<note place="margin">1 King. 19.4.</note> of the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Elijah,</hi> that he was perfectly cloy'd with Life, and pray'd for a diſmiſſion; he went a days Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney into the Wilderneſs, and came and ſat down un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Juniper Tree; and he requeſted for himſelf that he might die, and ſaid, <hi>It is enough now, O Lord, take away my Life; for I am not better than my Fathers.</hi> This looks like a Fit of Melancholy, occaſion'd by a Reflection on the unſucceſsfulneſs of his Miniſtry, and the rage of <hi>Jeza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> againſt him; and ſeems rather to be mention'd as an Inſtance of the Imperfections that ſtick to the beſt of Men in this Life, than to be propos'd for our Imitation, or to be drawn into Example by us.<note place="margin">Job 7.16.</note> The like Account the Holy Books give us of another Man, very Eminent for his Piety in the Age he liv'd in; that he loath'd Life, and was very deſirous an end might be put to it. The Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt this Example alſo is, that Holy <hi>Job</hi> breaks forth into this Expreſſion in the anguiſh and vexation of his Spirit; and that it was the mere effect of the preſſure of that load of Troubles and Evils under which he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd: Neither can this be deny'd; for the Holy Man ſeems hereupon, both to ground, and to excuſe his deſire of Death, as will be eaſily diſcern'd by any, who will be at the pains to conſult that Chapter; of which give me leave to give you a ſhort Paraphraſe, ſo far as concerns this his Complaint of Life, and earneſt deſire of Death. Let me ask you, ſays he to his Friends, theſe Queſtions; Is not Death appointed by the Soveraign Lord of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51435:3"/>World to every Man? And does not Man ſpin out his ſhort Life on Earth in trouble and toyl, like an Hireling his Day? And doth not ſuch an one, wearied out with the Work and Labour of the day, naturally deſire the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Night to give him eaſe and refreſhment? And is not this my Caſe, or rather, is not my Caſe much worſe? For both day and night are alike uneaſie to me; you cannot but be ſenſible into how miſerable a State I am fallen; you who have ſeen my former Proſperity (unleſs you have quite put off Humanity it ſelf) muſt pity my preſent Condition; and (which is to me a very ſad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration) you are never like to ſee it better; for I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy no more good in this Life; my Body is already over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run with Worms, and I am become loathſom while I live; and you cannot but be ſenſible how very difficult I find it to maintain my Temper of Mind in this Condition. Since therefore God has aſſign'd Death as the End of all theſe Miſeries; can you blame me, that I pray God to haſten it? I know that 'tis my Duty to refer my ſelf wholly to God's wiſe diſpoſal of me; but aſſure your ſelves, if God would give me leave to make my own choice, I would much rather deſire to die than to live: And I cannot but look upon this deſire as proceeding from Wiſdom, and a right Judgment of things. But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſpecial Circumſtances attending both theſe Caſes, there ſeems to be ſomething in the Requeſts of thoſe great Men, very agreeable to the deſires of the beſt Men, whilſt under theſe, wiſeſt, and moſt compos'd Thoughts, and the happieſt and moſt promiſing Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Life. A due Reflection upon the Vanity of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life in its beſt State, with a ſtedfaſt Faith of a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happy State, to ſucceed the determination of the ſhort Period of our days here on Earth, are enough to diſpoſe us, not to be over fond of living any very long time here; and, with ſubmiſſion to the Will and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, very chearfully to receive our Diſmiſſion, when ever it ſhall be ſent us. We ſo ſenſibly find, that there is no perfect Happineſs to be met with on Earth, that nothing needs to be ſaid to confirm our Experience; nor are we ignorant of the reſult of dying, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51435:3"/>that befal the Righteous; when once this Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is overcome. Happineſs is the thing that all humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is reaching at; and who would die ſtruglingly and with reluctancy, whilſt under the vigorous expectation of that great Declaration and Aſſurance given by our Religion? Rev. 14.13. <hi>And I heard a Voice from Heaven, ſaying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me Write, from henceforth, i. e.</hi> from the very time of their Deaths, <hi>bleſſed are the Dead which die in the Lord; yea ſaith the Spirit</hi> (which denotes the undoubted certainty of the thing) <hi>that they may reſt from their Labours, and their Works do follow them.</hi> The Scriptures therefore have given us other Inſtances leſs liable to theſe Exceptions; and which repreſent the deſire of Death, not as a raſh, unadviſed, impatient, or melancholy Requeſt, but as the effect of great Piety, high Attainments in Vertue and Goodneſs, and a very lively ſenſe of a future World; diſpoſing thoſe, who have thus rais'd themſelves above this World, and enlarg'd their Minds by the Principles of Religion, eaſily to part with all things here below; and to be under Wiſe, and Pious, and Devout Deſires of Death and Diſſolution. Such is the Inſtance of the great Apoſtle, who expreſſes his longing to be gone;<note place="margin">Phil. 1.21.</note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes peremptorily, that it was much for his Advantage to die; and though he was content to live, this was upon no other ſcore, but his being uſeful and ſerviceable to others: And he Pronounces this, as the common Deſire of all the Apoſtles, and very proper to be embrac'd by all Wiſe and Pious Chriſtians.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>We know that if the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly houſe of this tabernacle were diſſolv'd, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with Hands, eternal in the Heavens. For in this, q. d.</hi> for this Reaſon, <hi>we groan earneſtly, deſiring to be cloathed upon with our Houſe, which is from Heaven.</hi> And to mention no more, this was the Caſe of good old <hi>Simeon,</hi> a Juſt and Devout Man, as the Evangeliſt gives his Character, who had liv'd in the Faith and Hope of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the expectation of the Meſſias to come; and by the Account given of him, ſeems for ſome time to have been waiting, both for the fulfilling of this Hope; and for his own Diſſolution. For he had receiv'd a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, that he ſhould not die till the Meſſias ſhould
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51435:4"/>come, and he ſee him: In ſubmiſſion therefore to the Will of God, and in expectation of this Promiſe, he ſtill liv'd, not fond of Life, but chearfully waiting for Death, as the End of his Troubles here on Earth, and the beginning of a new and better Life; and coming into the Temple at the time that Jeſus was preſented to the Lord, according to the Cuſtom of the Law, he took the Child up in his Arms, and publickly declar'd, that this was the Meſſias ſo long promis'd; and the Revelation of his ſeeing him in the Fleſh being fulfill'd to him, he now expreſſes his hearty and earneſt deſire to be gathered to his Fathers in the Words of my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy Servant depart in peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which I might fairly Diſcourſe theſe Two things.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That it is very becoming a Wiſe Man, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially a Pious Chriſtian, to be very indifferent to Life, and to know when he has had enough of it; yea, to be weary of the World, and to be very willing to have his Diſmiſſion.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That it is a very deſirable thing to depart this Life in peace.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conſider only the Firſt Particular, and before I enter upon the Argument, I muſt ſet theſe following Bounds and Limitations to it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is to be underſtood with great deference to the Wiſdom and Providence of God, ſo as to ſhow no impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of Life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. With reſpect to the Benefit and Advantage of others, for whoſe ſake a Wiſe and Good Man, who is very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to die, may alſo be willing to live; yea, upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count he may be deſirous to live: when otherwiſe, and for his own ſake, he would make it his choice to die.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51435:4"/>
3. This deſire of Death is never to be divided from a firm perſuaſion of Mind, that whatever God orders to us, be it Life, or Death, is, for that reaſon, beſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is rather to be underſtood, as a deſire, that God would then take us out of this World, when, to his Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom, it ſhall appear to be moſt for our, and the Advantage of others, who depend upon us, or we have any relation to.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is to be underſtood with great deference to the Wiſdom and Providence of God, ſo as to ſhow no impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of Life. We are in this World like Soldiers in an Army, aſſign'd by their General to their ſeveral Poſts; which would be direct Diſobedience, proceeding from Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, Mutiny, or Cowardice, to deſert, without leave: And from what Cauſe ſoever it proceeds, it is highly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable. Such a Poſt is humane Life; which muſt not be abandon'd without permiſſion, and till the Providence of God diſcharge us. We muſt not be ſo weary of Life, or fond of Death, as voluntarily to forſake the one, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten the other by our own acts, or any means uſed upon our ſelves. This, I am aware, has of old been accounted a true Inſtance of a <hi>Roman</hi> Spirit of Magnanimity, and Greatneſs of Mind, for Men to diſpatch themſelves; and thereby put a period to thoſe Evils they were not able to bear: Thus the brave <hi>Cato</hi> ſlew himſelf, not being able to bear <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Victories, nor to endure to think of falling into the Conqueror's Hands. Thus <hi>Paulus Aemilius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to <hi>Perſeus,</hi> when he ſo meanly ſupplicated him that he might not be led in Triumph, That it had been, and was ſtill in his own Power to prevent this Diſgrace; and that it was the true mark of a Coward to have a Remedy at hand, and not to dare to uſe it. But as ſuch actions as theſe are utterly inconſiſtent with a ſteady Belief of God's Wiſe Government of the World; and, particularly, with the Principles of Chriſtianity; ſo neither are they In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of that Greatneſs of Mind they pretend to; they are rather plain Evidences of Puſillanimity, and Vileneſs of Mind; in that Men cannot bear Evils, as becomes Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51435:5"/>and eſpecially Chriſtians; but are prevail'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on baſely and meanly to fly from them; as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently argues in that noble Book of his, of tho City of God; where he maintains, that a voluntary Death is no Argument of Greatneſs of Mind.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It muſt be underſtood with reſpect to the Benefit and Advantage of others; for whoſe ſake, a wiſe and good Man, who is willing to die, may alſo be willing to live; yea, upon this account, be deſirous to live, when other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and for his own ſake, he would make it his choice to die.</p>
            <p>That which cauſes other Men to deſire their Lives, is a good reaſon to themſelves to deſire to live; at leaſt, to be ſo well content with this, as not to be weary of Life. When a Man is of more than ordinary Uſe and Benefit to the Common-wealth, or the Church of God, or in the Place where he lives, or when he has a numerous Family, and many young Children, who are growing up as Plants for the next Age; who receive a mighty Benefit by his careful Proviſion for them, by his Inſtruction, by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and by a great Diligence and Care uſed in their Education; and when, by the courſe of Nature, he might yet have liv'd many Years: In ſuch caſes it is very reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for others to deſire the Lives of ſuch Men: Sometimes the ſcarcity of ſuch Men, and the circumſtances of the time, when their Help and Aſſiſtance is like to be, in a ſpecial manner, beneficial to the World, renders it reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to be very earneſt in asking of God, their Lives: And thoſe are alſo good Reaſons why they themſelves ſhould deſire to live; living to the benefit of others, and ſo as to be uſeful in our Generations, being one great End of Life; and a conſiderable Reaſon why it is deſirable. And this was the very caſe of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which put him to ſuch a ſtruggle with himſelf, which to deſire. In reſpect of himſelf, it was paſt all diſpute, that Death was moſt deſirable; but in regard to thoſe, to whom his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry was ſerviceable, he was content to bear Life a little longer.<note place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>I am in a ſtrait,</hi> ſays he, <hi>betwixt two, having a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51435:5"/>nevertheleſs, to abide in the fleſh is more needful for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This deſire of Death is never to be divided from a firm perſuaſion of Mind, that whatever God orders to us, be it Life, or Death, is, for that Reaſon, beſt: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is rather to be underſtood as a deſire, that God would then take us out of this World; when, to his Infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, it ſhall appear to be moſt for our own, and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of others, who depend upon us, or we have any relation to. This is that great Principle, which alone can carry us chearfully through this World, and diſpoſe us to ſubmit freely, not only to the variety of Changes we meet with in it; but alſo to our great Change; and neither im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiently to expect it, nor yet to be ſtartled at it, when it comes. In our very judgment, as <hi>Epictetus</hi> ſpeaks, more to conſent to that, which God would have, than what our own Inclinations lead us to: To deſire and wiſh juſt ſo, as God doth: We may miſtake (and ſo may our Friends too, in their Opinion of things) when we imagine, that had we liv'd longer, we could have been very uſeful to the World; and done a great deal of good in it. God is the beſt Judge of this; and he is the Wiſe Diſpoſer of our Lives. 'Tis ſufficient for us, that we have done what good we could while we did live. We may be troubled for our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and Relations, for our little Children, and ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Friends, who enjoy'd a viſible Advantage by our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance amongſt them. We may be concern'd to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how hard it is like to be with our Oſſ-ſpring, and how many ſhocks they may indure after our departure. But, do we remember that we leave them to the Care of that Waking and Merciful Providence, of which we our ſelves have had ſo large an Experience all our Days. We may be wretchedly out, and often are ſo in our foreboding of Events. Their being depriv'd of our Help, and Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and Proviſion, renders them the more immediate Objects of Divine Providence; and it has been often ſeen, that Children, whom their Parents fear'd they had left in had Circumſtances, have in a wonderful manner, been better provided for when their Parents have been taken
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51435:6"/>away from them, than probably they would have been, had they continued with them; that Reflection, which the Holy <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> makes upon his own Life, being frequently verified in the Poſterity of good Men:<note place="margin">Pſalm 27.10.</note> 
               <hi>When my father and mother forſake me, the Lord taketh me up</hi> Again, we may think, that hitherto we have made but low attainments in Vertue, and Goodneſs; but could we have liv'd a little longer, we ſhould have been mighty Proficients in Chriſt's School; we could have got a much greater Conqueſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the World, and our ſelves; we could have enobled our Minds with more fixt and laſting Habits of Vertue; and, if God would be pleas'd to continue our Lives, we ſhould be much fitter for Heaven ſome few Years hence, than we are at preſent. But in this alſo we may be as much miſtaken, as in our other Thoughts. Have we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd that our Vertue, in this World, will always be very imperfect? Have we weighed what our Danger is, as long as we live here? Do we know, if we live longer, what fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Temptations we may meet with? or can we tell what Influence they may have upon us? or be ſure that they ſhall not prevail over us? And what do we think of that Declaration of the Prophet, which holds good under the Goſpel-Covenant:<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.24.</note> 
               <hi>When the righteous man forſakes his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and committeth iniquity, and doth as the wicked doth, his righteouſneſs that he hath done, ſhall not be mentioned: In his treſpaſs that he hath treſpaſſed, and in his ſin that he ſinneth, in that ſhall he die.</hi> It ſufficeth, that at preſent we walk ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and with Integrity, in the way of God's Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and that we heartily, and univerſally comply with our Duty, though in much weakneſs, and encompaſt with many infirmities: The reſt is to be left intirely to the Wiſdom of God: And when he calls us out of the World, we may hope, and (in as much as all things are order'd by Infinite Wiſdom, and God's Goodneſs is over all his Works) have reaſon to believe, that this is the moſt fitting time for us to die in, and beſt alſo for thoſe, who belong to us, and for the World in general. Having fixt theſe Bounds to it, I now proceed to the Argument it ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51435:6"/>
That it is very becoming a wiſe Man, and eſpecially a Pious Chriſtian, to be very indifferent to Life, and to know when he has had enough of it; yea, to be weary of the World; and to be very willing to have his Diſmiſſion. Many Conſiderations offer themſelves for the evincing the Truth of this Propoſition; ſome reſpect a wiſe Man bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider'd as ſuch; others concern him as he is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. I ſhall name ſome few of both ſorts: Thoſe that reſpect a wiſe Man barely conſider'd as ſuch, are theſe following:
<list>
                  <item>I. A juſt and impartial Reflection upon the ſtate of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature.</item>
                  <item>II. A Conſideration of the future Contingencies of Life.</item>
                  <item>III. A view of Death, with reſpect to the Good and Evil of Life.</item>
                  <item>IV. That univerſal Law, That all, who are born, muſt die.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. A juſt and impartial Reflection upon the ſtate of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature. That this is very Deplorable, has been the loud Complaint of all the Ages of the World; which has been made by the wiſeſt Men, who have moſt narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider'd Man's Condition in all his various Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: And though there are many Goods in Life, which are not moroſely, and with ſullenneſs to be deſpis'd; yea, it is an Inſtance of great Folly to rank them in the number of indifferent things; yet it has been generally agreed, that the Evils of Life do much over-balance the Good: And though perhaps this is not ſo, in reſpect of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry individual Man; for ſome are in very happy outward Circumſtances in reſpect of others: Yet, if we conſider how it fares with the generality, (which we muſt do, in duly examining the Caſe of humane Nature) upon this view, there is no great doubt to be made, but the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation will be found to be as true as 'tis common, and 'tis
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51435:7"/>a Wiſe Man's part, not barely to conſider his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Circumſtances, but to enquire how it goes with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men; ſince (humane Nature being common to all) whatever any other Man's Condition is, he cannot tell how ſoon his may be the ſame. When thou art lifted up with admiration of thy ſelf, for the Pomp wherein thou appeareſt to the World, caſt thy Eyes downwards upon thoſe who are cloathed in Rags, and want the Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Life: When thou art wandring, ſays the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, at <hi>Xerxes</hi> croſſing the Ocean with his mighty Navy; think of thoſe Wretches who are digging through Mount <hi>Athos,</hi> who are forc'd to their Labour with Blows, and Blood mingled with their Sweat; call to mind that they had their Ears and Noſes cut off, becauſe the Bridge was broken down by the violence of the Waves; and conſider what ſecret Reflections they make upon their ſad Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>'Tis enough to cauſe a Wiſe Man readily to embrace Death,<note place="margin">Job 3.17.</note> to conſider only <hi>Job</hi>'s Deſcription of the Grave: <hi>There the wicked ceaſe from troubling; there the weary are at reſt. There the priſoners reſt together, they hear not the voice of the oppreſſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Conſideration of the future Contingencies of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life. Theſe are without Number, and yet the daily expectation of every Wiſe Man, who has conſider'd, what is repreſented by the Emblem of the Wheel, conſtant change and viciſſitude in the Life of Man. We are, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, very Rich; but do we know how long we ſhall be ſo? and may we not, ere we are aware, be as Poor; <hi>Riches make themſelves wings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 23.5.</note> 
               <hi>they fly away as an Eagle to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven,</hi> ſo ſays the Wiſeſt of Men. We are at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in perfect health, brisk and lively, and full of vigour; but may not our Conſtitution ſoon be broken, and we caſt upon a Bed of Sickneſs, grapling with Pains, or crying out under extream Torture. We enjoy Liberty, and have a quiet Poſſeſſion of the Bleſſings of Life; but is it impoſſible that ever we ſhould fall under the Yoke of ſome of the mighty <hi>Nimrods</hi> of the World, the Hunters of Mankind?<note place="margin">Job 7.15.</note> When, as <hi>Job</hi> expreſſes it, we ſhould
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51435:7"/>chooſe ſtrangling rather than Life. <hi>i. e.</hi> If we were at our own diſpoſe, the worſt of Deaths would be far more deſirable than ſuch a Life. When <hi>Xerxes</hi> viewing his nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Army, bemoan'd it, that within a little more than half an Age there would not be a Man of them left alive; one of his Captains reply'd, Sir, <hi>Let not this trouble you, for they are like to endure ſo great fatigue, and ſo many hardſhips, that the greater number will, in all proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, wiſh themſelves dead, a long time before they ſhall be ſo happy as to die.</hi> And thus the <hi>Roman</hi> Orator, comparing the Great <hi>Pompey</hi>'s Sickneſs at <hi>Naples,</hi> where he had like to have died, with his laſt End, concludes, That it had been much better for this Great Man to have died, when he had the Command of the Arms of <hi>Rome,</hi> and was the darling of the World; for this had prevented the Bloody War with <hi>Caeſar;</hi> the loſs of his Army; his flying with Diſgrace; his being ſlain by one of his own Servants; the preſenting his Head to his Father-in-Law; his Children turning Fugitive, and the Conſiſcation of his Eſtate, but he had dyed in Honour, and never known any of theſe Evils: neither himſelf nor his Family. And upon this account was that wiſe ſaying of <hi>Solon</hi> to <hi>Croeſus,</hi> who had cauſe enough afterward to remember and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Truth of it, That he muſt firſt ſee him die before he judged of his Happineſs; it being a Point of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Wiſdom, to account no Man happy before his Death.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A view of Death, with reſpect to the Good and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of this Life. 'Tis true, Death deprives us of all thoſe, which are properly called the Goods of Life: But, as theſe are not over Conſiderable, ſo it is our preſent want of them that renders them of any Conſideration at all: If we did not need them, their abſence would be no injury to us in this Life; the true Notion of Riches, being a ſufficiency to anſwer our Conveniencies; beyond which all is but meer imagination, and attended with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of trouble. Since therefore Death puts us in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, that we cannot want them, and perfectly takes away their uſe, what trouble can it be that it removes us
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51435:8"/>from them. To look upon it as a very uncomfortable thing, to be caſt into Circumſtances, where we cannot uſe theſe Goods, is to be ſo drowned in ſenſuality, that we are thereby become fit for nothing beyond this World, and hardly fit for this. But then Death takes us alſo from the Evils of Life, which are more in Number than the Goods, and much over-balance them, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, at leaſt to the generality of Mankind. A bare enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration of the Evils of Life, does ſufficiently, in <hi>Tully</hi>'s Opinion, commend Death, which puts an end to them. He tells us of one, who writing a Book in the praiſe of Death, did therein only deſcribe the Calamities of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life: On this Account Death has been ſometimes interpreted as a Reward for Eminent Piety. The very Heathens ſeemed to have looked upon it under this Notion. Thus when thoſe who built the Magnificent Temple of <hi>Apollo,</hi> prayed that what was beſt for Man, might befal them, the third day after they were found dead; which was reckoned upon as a Reward of their Piety. Agreeably to this,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 57.1.</note> the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ſpeaking of the Death of Good <hi>Joſias,</hi> ſays, <hi>He was taken away from the Evil to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Univerſal Law upon humane Nature, that all who are born muſt die. It has ever been accounted a great part of Wiſdom, to bring our Minds quietly to comport with what is not in our Power to avoid. By this Conſideration we bear up under all the diſaſters of Life; this brings us into Temper, when we have royl'd our ſelves never ſo much, upon the death of our neareſt Relations, or deareſt Friends: And the ſame Thought ought, in common Diſcretion, to bring us at leaſt, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to ſubmit to our own Deaths, whenever they come. This is the great Argument that runs through all the Books of the Moraliſts: A Pilate, ſays <hi>Plutarch,</hi> cannot in a Storm command the Billows, or calm the Winds; or, by Hectoring, cauſe the Storm to ceaſe; he at laſt therefore commits himſelf to its Fury; pulls down all his Sails by the Board, and expects the ſinking of the Leaky Veſſel; and thus muſt we, when Life grows painful and uneaſie, and Death approaches, wait our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51435:8"/>Diſſolution, according to the Common Law of Nature; ſince that which is unavoidable, ought to diſturb us as little as is poſſible. This is the Principal Argument of all <hi>Seneca</hi>'s Books of the Brevity of Life, and the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of the Mind, and his Diſcourſes of Providence, That it is a very unbecoming thing to ſtruggle with the Laws of Fate, and not to be carried willingly, whither we muſt go whether we will or no. But far greater reaſon have we for this, who are taught, what a Vertue it is, and how capable of Reward, chearfully to ſubmit to the Wiſdom of God, in diſpoſing of our Lives; and theſe are ſuch Arguments, as are proper to induce a Wiſe Man not to be over fond of Life, and to know when he has enough of it; and, at leaſt, quietly and calmly to entertain the Meſſage of Death, when it is ſent to him. But then a Pious Chriſtian has Arguments beyond all theſe, to do not only thus much, but a great deal more; to be perfectly above any fondneſs for Life, and to rejoice at the Thoughts of his Diſſolution; and, with ſubmiſſion to the Will and Providence of God, heartily to deſire his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; and they are theſe following.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. A General Conſideration of the Religion we Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, which has chiefly a reſpect to a future World.</item>
               <item>II. Our Knowledge that the Sting of Death is pulled out.</item>
               <item>III. The Thoughts of being abſolutely and perfectly freed from Sin.</item>
               <item>IV. The enlargement of our Faculties and Perfection of our Vertue.</item>
               <item>V. The immediate Poſſeſſion of Happineſs at Death.</item>
               <item>VI. The Completion of this in Body and Soul at the General Judgment.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51435:9"/>
1. A General Conſideration of the Religion we Profeſs, which has chiefly a reſpect to a future World. The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion Promiſes us very little or nothing that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects meerly this preſent Life: In this it differs from God's Ancient Covenant with the Jews, that it ſecures us of nothing of this World abſolutely, but requires us to refer all things to God's Wiſdom and Providence to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them to us, as they ſhall beſt tend to the making us wiſe and good; and to the ſitting of us for what we are deſigned in another World. Hence Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is ſaid not to be <hi>of this World:</hi> hence we are direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to look upon our ſelves as <hi>Pilgrims and Strangers on this Earth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 13.36. Heb. 11.13. 1 Pet. 2.11. Heb. 13.14. Phil. 3.20.</note> that we are put in Mind, that we have here <hi>no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing City;</hi> and are exhorted to be in the continual ſearch after <hi>one that is to come;</hi> that we are counſelled to <hi>Set our Affections on things above, and not on things on the earth;</hi> to have our <hi>Converſation in another World:</hi> That is, to behave our ſelves as thoſe who expect a Portion and an Intereſt there; and if we conſider a great number of the Goſpel Precepts, and weigh thoſe high degrees of Vertue they oblige us to; and to deny our ſelves in a great many Inſtances, which are very hard and difficult, and yet not altogether neceſſary for this World; yea ſometimes to hate and deſpiſe this World, and to chuſe the greateſt Evils of Life; together with thoſe Duties of over-looking our own Advantage for the greater Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of others; of doing Good for Evil, of waſting our Spirits, and laying out the Strength and Vigour of our Days, in doing good to Mankind; we cannot but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that theſe Rules have a reſpect to ſome future World; and that they are deſigned to raiſe us up to ſuch a Temper of Mind, as may prepare us for ſomething God has intended us for, when there ſhall be an end of this Life of Man upon Earth. Neither can we poſſibly have any doubt of this, who believe the Chriſtian Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; the Promiſes whereof have ſo direct a reference to a Future State of things. This Faith was the great ſupport to the Primitive Chriſtians, under thoſe hard Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances they were in: Their Thoughts were ſix'd upon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51435:9"/>ſuch Promiſes as theſe,<note place="margin">Revel. 3.5.21. —21.7. —22.5.</note> 
               <hi>Him that overcometh will I cloath in white rayment, and I will not blot out his name out of the Book of Life; and I will confeſs him before my Father, and he ſhall ſit down with me in my Throne, even as I have overcome, and am ſet down with my Father in his Throne; and he ſhall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit all things, and he ſhall reign with me for ever and ever.</hi> Hence it was, that they were ſuch great Inſtances of Vertue, ſuch Bright and Shining Lights to the World, ſuch Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Examples of a mighty Zeal for God, of an ardent Piety and Devotion, of the moſt heroick Goodneſs, the moſt enlarged Charity; an exemplary Patience, and a very intire Reſignation of themſelves to the Will of God. Hence it was that they ſo readily parted with their Lives, and ſo willingly choſe to die, to the amazement of the Heathen World; who obſerved of them, that it was the belief of a Life after this, that was the Cauſe of all this Courage and Reſolution; who therefore would not ſometimes ſuffer them to be buried, but burnt their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and diſperſed their Aſhes; fooliſhly thinking, that this would abate their Hope of a Reſurrection. Now if this be the great thing that the Chriſtian Inſtitution teaches us, That this World is not our home, but that we live here expectants of one to come; What great reaſon have we to be fond of this Life? Or who can blame any Man for deſiring and courting Death upon theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples? What is related of <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> when he died, whether ever ſaid by him or no, does very well become a dying Chriſtian, expreſſing his future Hopes and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations. <hi>I have hitherto lived an Exile from my Country, but now I am going ſafely thither; I am returning to that Bleſſed City, whither we cannot paſs, without taking Death in our way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The having the Sting of Death pulled out for us. Death muſt be allowed to be very terrible to a wicked Man; for when he dieth, <hi>His hope periſheth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 11.7.</note> 
               <hi>his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is utterly cut off.</hi> There's an end of all that, in which he has placed his Confidence; the Man who has Calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all his Projects, and deſigns meerly for this World, muſt needs be ſtrangely ſurprized, when the Meſſage is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51435:10"/>brought him, that God requires his Soul, and that he muſt give up his Account, and his Stewardſhip (for ſo the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calls this Life) is at an end: But the loſs of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Enjoyments is not all; he goes out of this World in a State of Guilt, and is haled to the Divine Tribunal, and there Sentenced to a Puniſhment, we know little more of, than this, That it is certainly a very Terrible one; and probably greater than we can at preſent conceive it to be; 'Tis far otherwiſe with the Good Man; he parts with nothing that is overvaluable to him, having never enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Affections to what he always knew, was to be left in a few days; and he goes out of the World with his Sins Pardoned, and delivered from the Threatnings annext to the Law; and this is that pulling out the Sting of Death, which we owe to the Merits and Satisfaction of our Bleſſed Saviour; in Conſideration of which, a Chriſtian may look on Death as a hurtleſs thing, whoſe wounding Power is taken away, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us in that Triumphal Song, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55. <hi>O Death where is thy Sting? O Grave where is thy Victory? The Sting of Death is Sin, and the Strength of Sin is the Law; but thanks be to God, who giveth us the Victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Thoughts of being abſolutely and perfectly freed from Sin.</p>
            <p>All the Evils and Miſeries of this Life put together, are not half ſo much a Burden to a Pious Chriſtian, as the ſharp Conteſt that is kept up within him, betwixt the Fleſh and the Spirit: The ſtruggle betwixt the Principles of Grace and thoſe of a Corrupt Nature; and the Advantage which the Devil, and Temptations, and his own Evil Inclinations, not perfectly ſubdued, often get of him, through the Remainders of Sin in him. Theſe are Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of his daily Sorrow; and Repentance, and Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and he often Trembles for thoſe Sins he has fallen into, though long ſince; and which yet he hopes he has truly Repented of, and to his very laſt Breath, continues to <hi>work out his Salvation with fear:</hi> And though he uſes all Diligence,<note place="margin">Heb 6.11.</note> according to the Apoſtle's Advice, to <hi>reach to the full aſſurance of hope unto the end;</hi> yet he confiders
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51435:10"/>that this is a Modeſt and Humble ſort of Aſſurance, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, and ſo very well conſiſtent with ſome Fear. Now Death is deſirable by a ſincere Chriſtian on this Account, that it ſets him above all his Troubles and his Fears: It puts him into a State where the Devil ſhall have no further Advantage againſt him, where this ſtruggling betwixt Grace and Nature ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ceaſe, where he ſhall no more diſhonour God, nor blemiſh his own Nature; nor have ſo much as the Sins of Infirmity to lament and bewail, but ſhall live in a perfect freedom from thoſe Moral Evils, which created ſo much uneaſineſs to him, and ſo often put him in hazard in this Life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Enlargement of our Faculties, and Perfection of our Vertue.</p>
            <p>How ſhort Humane Knowledge is, they beſt underſtand who have ſpent the longeſt Time, and uſed the greateſt Pains in improving it; they who know almoſt nothing, may perhaps eſteem themſelves very great Clerks: If by chance they light upon a thing, which every one does not know, they preſently have a very great Opinion of their own Underſtanding; and (like the Son of <hi>Syrach</hi>'s Deſcription of a Fool, <hi>That he travelleth with a word</hi>) are very big, to let other Men ſee how very wiſe they are, of a ſudden, grown; whilſt thoſe, who know the moſt things knowable in this State, have very different Thoughts of themſelves; and, though they avoid ſuch a Scepticiſm, as to doubt of every thing; yet are they very ſenſible how many things there are which they know not, and how far they are from perfectly underſtanding very Common things: So alſo a little Phariſaick Piety makes a very fine ſhew, and a mighty noiſe and bluſter in the World: They who are got no further than this empty Form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are highly opiniated of themſelves, and apt to deſpiſe all others as meer Sons of the Earth, not worth regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Whereas a truly Pious Chriſtian, is always a Humble Chriſtian; he has a very mean Opinion of himſelf, and is very ready to entertain a good one of other Men; he is ſenſible of the Imperfection of his Vertue, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51435:11"/>what low Degrees of it he has attained to; and his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Comfort is grounded upon his Sincerity; and that he hopes and truſts, that his Heart is right towards God. Now who would be fond of this Life, which is ſo dark and ſo imperfect a State? Who would not be willing to die, that expects the enlargement of his Knowledge upon his Diſſolution, extending to a clear view of all the Works of God, and looking into the Secrets, and unfolding the Myſteries of Providence, to the near Contemplation of the Divine Nature, ſeeing God as he is, and comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Perfections, as much as Angels do, and to the Fathoming the Wonders of our Redemption by Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; things ſo far out of the reach of our Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in this World; where alſo he ſhall arrive at Degrees of Vertue infinitely above what he is ever capable of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to here: And, in one word, ſhall be, in all things, like unto the Angels of God which are in Heaven; and how happy may he conceive himſelf then to be? who conſiders, that he owes the chief pleaſure of his preſent Life, to the ſmall Attainments he has been able to make in Wiſdom and Goodneſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The immediate Poſſeſſion of Happineſs at Death.</p>
            <p>Indeed if all Pious Chriſtians (ſome few only excepted) were to enter immediately upon Death, into a Place of the moſt exquiſite Torment, differing very little from Hell, ſaving in the infinite duration of it, and there to abide, none knows how long, even to the Day of the Great Judgment, ſome of them; it would be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable for any Man to deſire Death, unleſs it were by Martyrdom, by which he might eſcape this Purgatory Fire; and the thought of dying would be the moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful one that a Man could have in his whole Life: But this is a meer Fiction, brought into the Church by Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Superſtition, and maintained for Reaſons well known; and has no Foundation neither in Scripture or Primitive Antiquity; defended by ſome, even of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, only as ſome other Doctrines are, becauſe Decreed in Councils, and ſo not to be let go, for fear of ſhaking a Pretence, that is not to be parted
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51435:11"/>with. The Scripture is, in this Point, very clear and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, and aſſures us, that immediately upon Death, there is an admiſſion to Bliſs. <hi>To day,</hi> ſays our Saviour to the Thief on the Croſs, <hi>ſhalt thou be with me in paradiſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 23.43. Phil. 3.23.</note> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> mentions his being with Chriſt, as an immediate conſequence of his Departure. Theſe are ſo plain Proofs, that, to evade the force of them, they muſt be exempt Caſes; and the Thief, and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſome few more, never went to Purgatory. But this ſhift ſignifies little, for the Scripture ſpeaks of all that die in the Lord; that is, in the Faith and Obedience of the Goſpel, as being at reſt; which is a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Idiom, and imports a ſtate of Bliſs. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> takes notice, that living here, keeps us from Chriſt, and therefore aſſigns this as a Reaſon, why we ſhould be willing and deſirous to leave this World, that we might go to Chriſt:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.6, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Knowing that whilſt we are at home in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, we are abſent from the Lord: We are therefore confident and willing, rather to be abſent from the body, and to be preſent with the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The completion of this Happineſs in Body and Soul at the General Judgment.</p>
            <p>Though good Men are admitted to immediate Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at Death, yet not to a full Participation of it, or to all that Happineſs God has deſigned them, by way of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: This is reſerved for that Great Day, ſo often made mention of in the Holy Books, when Chriſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.31.</note> to whom the Judgment of the World is committed, ſhall come in the Glory of his Father, in Triumph, and with great Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, attended with an innumerable Hoſt of Angels,<note place="margin">Acts 1.11. 1 Theſſ. 4.16.</note> to render to every Man according to his Works. Then ſhall thoſe who ſleep in the Duſt awake, and the Dead ſhall be called out of their Graves, by the Voice of the Son of Man, and the Sound of the laſt Trump. Theſe Bodies of ours ſhall then be raiſed up from Mortality, and Corruption, to an Immortal and Incorruptible State; A wonderful thing, to be effected by that Power alone, which firſt made all things out of nothing: A Truth knowable only by <hi>Revelation,</hi> and received by <hi>Faith;</hi> and being united to their proper Souls, together with them, who ſhall then be found
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51435:12"/>alive, and remaining on the Earth, we ſhall be caught up in the Clouds,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4.17.</note> to meet the Lord in the Air, and ſo ſhall we ever be with the Lord. This is that great Day, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.8.</note> when Crowns ſhall be put upon the Heads of all the Faithful; even all thoſe who love his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing. This is the Day, when the whole World ſhall have its laſt Period and Conſummation; when Death it ſelf ſhall be Eternally deſtroyed; and God's Kingdom ſhall be ſet up over all,<note place="margin">Revel. 20.14.</note> and his Saints ſhall Reign with him for ever and ever. And theſe I take to be good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for every Pious Chriſtian to be indifferent to Life, and very willing, with ſubmiſſion to God's Wiſdom in Diſpoſing of him, to have his Diſmiſſion.</p>
            <p>Now the Uſe of this Doctrine, is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To endeavour to reduce it to Practice. I mean to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry our ſelves, with all that indifferency towards this World, and Life, and preſent ſtate of Things, which becomes wife Men, and good Chriſtians. We cannot diſpoſe of Events: What belongs to us, is to be content with that Portion, whatever it is, that Providence allots us, and to manage every thing to the beſt advantage, and to take care that what befals us, without our leave, may not diſturb us. It is not worth the while, for gaining the World, to do any thing, not only, which is plainly Unjuſt; but any thing, that is Uncharitable, Mean, Pitiful, or Baſe: And what we poſſeſs fairly, and honeſtly, it is Wiſdom ſo to uſe, as not to abuſe it;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.11.</note> remembring, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, That the Faſhion of this World paſſeth away: Neither to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver anxious and ſollicitous about it, nor to ſuffer our whole Life to be eat up with the Cares and Concerns of it, nor ſo to ſet our Hearts and Affections upon it, as that it ſhould ever prove horribly troubleſome, and uneaſie to us to part with it: To avoid that Error, our Saviour cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in <hi>Martha,</hi> To be always Carking about things little and needleſs; and with her wiſer Siſter, to be careful to ſecure to our ſelves that better part,<note place="margin">Luke 10.40, 41, 42.</note> thoſe vertuous Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and Habits of the Mind, which ſhall never be taken away from us. To conſider this World as only of preſent
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51435:12"/>Uſe; and when the time comes, that this Uſe is to ceaſe, to take our leaves of it, as a thing we are no further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in. If we enjoy the Good of Life, to receive it Thankfully, and manage it with Diſcretion, and ſo as it may turn to our Advantage hereafter. If we have our ſhare in the Evils of Life, to bear theſe with Moderation, and Patience, as expecting better things to come. And, as to Life it ſelf, neither to be Prodigal, nor Niggardly of it; to eſteem it neither above, nor below its juſt Value; to take care to preſerve it, as far as becomes a wiſe Man; and yet to be ready to part with it upon a good account; to prefer the keeping the Integrity of our Minds and a good Conſcience before it; but yet to chuſe to die, though a violent and immature Death, rather than do an ill thing to prolong Life; the doing of which is a far greater Evil, than Death can be to a good Man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In order to this, it ought to be our great and main en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, to live up to the height of the Principles of that Religion we profeſs. <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us of one, who leading a very looſe life, conſulted the Oracle, Whether ever he ſhould live any better; to which the Anſwer was, That it ſhould be better with him after he was dead. Not long after this he dies; but while they were carrying him forth to be buryed, of a ſudden, he Revives, and comes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: But it was almoſt incredible, what a Change there was in the courſe of his Life; he became one of the moſt Pious and Verthous Men of his Age, and being asked, by his Friends, the Reaſon of this great Change, he gave them this account of it, That no ſooner was his Soul parted from his Body, but he found a mighty confuſion in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which he could not compare to any thing better, than the Pilot of a Ship being flung from the Helm, by the force of a Storm, into the vaſt Ocean; after this, riſing up, as it were above Water, and recovering himſelf from this Confuſion, he thought he felt himſelf alive, and, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing round him, he ſaw all things clearly; but very different ſights they were, from what he had ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held in this World: Amongſt other things, he ſaw a numerous Company of Souls, in very different ſtates;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51435:13"/>ſome in mighty Tranſports of Joys, others in Miſeries inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible: Some of theſe latter, whom he thought he knew, he endeavoured to have approached and diſcourſed them; but they ſeemed to be like Perſons frighted and bereav'd of their Senſes, in a deep Conſternation flying from him, and wholly avoiding him: At laſt he meets with a certain Kinſman of his, who had been for ſome time dead, who calls him by his Name, and gives him a large Account of that State, and carries him about, and makes him an Eye Witneſs of the ſeveral Conditions of ſeparate Souls; but withal tells him, That he was not in the Number of the Dead, but by permiſſion only was come hither, and muſt return again to his Body. Whilſt he ſtood trembling at what he had ſeen, a certain Woman, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable for her Form, took him by the Hand, and bad him keep in Remembrance theſe things. The Moral of this Story inſtructs us, what influence a direct view of another World is fitted to have upon us; and what then may not be expected from us, who have ſo full and clear a Revelation of it, and of the ſeveral States of Men, when arrived there? Let us then walk by this Faith, and have our Eyes fixed upon the Recompence of a future Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Let us remember, that the great deſign of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is to Train us up for Heaven; and that all the great things it has promiſed, are to be accompliſhed and perfected in a future World: Let us look upon our ſelves as only paſſing through this, and travelling home to our Fathers Houſe, whither our Forerunner is already gone, and where Manſions of Glory are prepared for us; ſuch Weights of Glory, as the Apoſtle did not know how to expreſs, exceeding Eternal weights of Glory: Let us often converſe with that World, the World of Angels and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirits; a World of perfect Knowledge and Vertue, of Goodneſs and Charity; a Region of Pure and Spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Light, where God himſelf has his peculiar Throne; where there is no need of the Sun, nor of the Moon to ſhine in it;<note place="margin">Rev. 21.21.</note> for the Glory of God does lighten it, <hi>and the Lamb is the Light thereof.</hi> Let our Hearts be much there where our chief Treaſure is, where our conſummated Happineſs lies; ſo ſhall we be able to preſerve a Wiſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51435:13"/>and Pious Indifferency to this World and Life, ſo ſhall we take care to live as uſefully, and do as much good as we can in the World; ſo ſhall we always keep our ſelves in an actual Preparation for Death; and, whenever it comes, being born up by the ſtrength of our Faith and Hope in God, and in his Promiſes, we ſhall cheatfully take up this Pious Hymn of good Old <hi>Simeon,</hi> and ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy Servant depart in peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſenſible I have been too long upon this Subject, in regard there is another I know you will expect I ſhould ſpeak ſomething to: But if I beg a little of your Patience, I know not when I ſhall do this again; and I am pretty well aſſured, never upon ſo ſad an Occaſion. I am well aware how liable Diſcourſes of this Nature are to Cenſure and Exception: But in this Auditory, upon the preſent Occaſion, I am above theſe fears. It is allowed by all, that there is a juſt Praiſe due to thoſe who have raiſed themſelves above a common Level: I do not mean in amaſſing together a more than ordinary heap of Riches, the Portion as commonly of Fools as of the Wiſe, and at leaſt equally reached by Good and Bad Men; but in thoſe Gifts of true Wiſdom and real Goodneſs, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt God has given to Men; by which there ſeems to be as great a difference amongſt Men, as betwixt Man and the Beaſts, or as betwixt ſome Men of exalted Vertue and the Angels above: For while ſome are raiſed up to a Divine Likeneſs, others have almoſt quite defaced the Image of God in themſelves, and are ſunk a vaſt way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Dignity of Humane Nature, into Ignorance, Folly, Immorality, and downright Brutiſhneſs: Such who have been thus diſtinguiſhed from others in their Lives, ought to be ſo in their Deaths too; and not to go out of the World without a more than ordinary notice taken of them: 'Tis fit that their Wiſdom and Vertue, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them ſo uſeful while they lived, ſhould be propoſed to the World as an Example, and for the imitation of ſuch as ſurvive them. This has been the Practice of all Nations, to have Orations of Praiſe, at the Interment of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51435:14"/>ſuch who lived uſefully in their Generations. The Scripture mentions it as an Act of Honour done to the Righteous at their Deaths, and ſeems very plainly to recommend it in thoſe Promiſes to the Good Man,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 32.33.</note> 
               <hi>That his Name ſhall be had in remembrance, and his Memory be bleſſed.</hi> The Practice of the Chriſtian Church in this Point is ſo well known, that I ſhall not ſpend time needleſly to inſiſt on it. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by this Authority, I will venture to draw a ſhort Character of your Deceaſed Paſtor. He was a Man of a very large Underſtanding, of a quick and ready Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and had a very happy way of expreſſing himſelf, which, as far as theſe are meer Natural Endowments, do, by no means, ſeem to be given by God to all Men alike; and would tempt to believe, that the difference in Men does not wholly ariſe from the Diſpoſition of Bodily Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans or Education, or any the like Cauſes, but that there is really an inequality in their Original make. Theſe natural Endowments were cultivated by a happy Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and an early Acquaintance with all that School Learning, which is ſo neceſſary a Foundation for rendring a Man uſeful in any conſiderable Poſt in Church or State: He was called very early out, to be a Labourer in God's Vineyard; an Employment (though ſome perhaps may imagine little of difficulty in it, and that the Clergy, of all other Men, live moſt at eaſe) that requires a mighty Pains, to be able to diſcharge it wiſely and uſefully; which perhaps the Apoſtle intimates, when he calls it <hi>Labouring in the Word and Doctrine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.17.</note> Our Deceaſed Brother was ſo apprehenſive of this at his firſt coming among you, where his conſtant Task was to preach three times a Week; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Monthly Preparation Sermon for the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and many other occaſional Sermons; that to be able to give a good Account of his Miniſtry to God, to his own Conſcience, and to Wiſe Men; to approve himſelf <hi>a Workman that needed not to be aſhamed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>rightly dividing the word of Truth;</hi> and that as becomes the Man of God, he might <hi>be perfect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>throughly furniſhed to every good work,</hi> as the Apoſtle exhorts <hi>Timothy;</hi> that is as a Teacher or Preacher of the Goſpel, by the Study of the Scripture, be furniſhed for all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51435:14"/>turns, and enabled to diſcharge his whole Duty towards the Souls of his Flock, as Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> has Paraphraſed thoſe Words; he fell upon that exceſſive hard Study, which broke an excellent Conſtitution of Body, and ſo impaired his Health, that he was never able to recover it; and though he was in a while ſenſible of this, and often admoniſhed by his Friends to remit that Rigour, yet his Circumſtances partly neceſſitated him to continue it; and beſides, by Uſe and Cuſtom, it was become ſo pleaſant a Diverſion, that he ſeemed to think the Improvements hereby made to himſelf, to be an abundant Recompenſe for the Infirmities it brought along with it; and, as <hi>Tully</hi> preferred the living one Day according to the Precepts of Philoſophy, to a vicious Immortality; ſo our Deceaſed Brother had a far greater Inclination to improve his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and to live uſefully, though but a few years, than to arrive at an extream old Age, with no other Sign upon him that he had lived long, but what might be diſcovered, as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaks, in Wrinkles and Grey Hairs. This I have particular Reaſon to obſerve, inaſmuch, as when I have been diſcourſing with him, which was frequently, of giving himſelf a little caſe, and calling in one to his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, his conſtant Anſwer was to this Effect, That his Life could not be better waſted than in a careful diſcharge of his Miniſtry, and in doing all the Good he could; and let his Great Maſter call him when he pleaſed, <hi>Happy was that Servant, whom his Lord, when he ſhould come, found ſo doing.</hi> In Conſideration of this, his hard Study was not barely to ſatisfie his Curioſity, or to pleaſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with his own Notions (though this is both an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and a very delightful Piece of Epicuriſm;) but to render himſelf ſerviceable to others, to diſcharge his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice with Credit to Religion; and to profit thoſe in truſt committed to his Care, he was a Conſtant, Judicious and Profitable Preacher. In all his Diſcourſes he Studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly avoided, according to the Apoſtle's Advice, <hi>all uſeleſs Queſtions, which miniſter only to ſtrife;</hi> and by which (let the Preacher argue and defend either ſide of the Queſtion) none are made either the wiſer or better Men. His chief Buſineſs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51435:15"/>was to proſecute Practical Subjects, with the utmoſt force of Perſwaſion; well knowing, that moſt Men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their Duty, much better than they Practiſe it; and that to ſtir up their Remembrance, and over-rule their Wills, was one great part of the Miniſter's Office. His main Endeavour was to ſpeak good Senſe, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the moſt uſeful Truths in plain and eaſie Expreſſions; and was often wont to ſay, That the Practical Doctrines of Chriſtianity, were ſo perfectly agreeable to natural Principles, that if they were fairly repreſented, no Man would be found to make the leaſt oppoſition to them; but that the ſame Doctrine; might be ſo intangled with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, under the ſhew of clearing them, that Mens Prejudices would ſtill over-ſway them, and every Man would retain the Principles of his firſt Education; and that ſuch Diſcourſes never turned to any Advantage of the Hearers, but ſerved either to Prejudice them againſt their Preachers, or to drive them into Heats and Contentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, to the bane of Chriſtian Practice. We are lately told of a Noble Deſign, provided for in the Will of a very extraordinary Perſon Deceaſed, that every year ſhould be compoſed a few well Digeſted Sermons, wherein ſhould be ſet forth the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion in General, without deſcending to the Subdivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions among Chriſtians: This is very agreeable to what was the conſtant Deſign of your Deceaſed Paſtor; whoſe chief Buſineſs it was to repreſent Chriſtianity, <hi>As a Syſtem of Truths, which ought to purifie the Hearts, and govern the Lives of thoſe who Profeſs it;</hi> where the Fundamentals of Chriſtianity were in hazard, none ſhewed a greater Zeal in exhorting earneſtly to <hi>contend for the Faith once delivered to the Saints;</hi> witneſs his many cloſe Diſcourſes againſt Popery in the late Reign: And, as he apprehended there might be in time occaſion for it, he was ready to ſhew the ſame Zeal againſt ſuch Errors, as threaten utter Ruine to all Poſitive Religion: But, in other Matters, he abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Bigotry; and knew how to pity the weakneſs of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Underſtandings, and to allow for the Prejudices of Education; and though no Man had a greater value for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51435:15"/>our Church Conſtitution, nor could more heartily wiſh the Recovery of our Diſcipline; nor yet had a truer, and righter Notion of Religion; yet he never cared, roughly to diſturb People, though in an Error; when he ſaw the Error did no hurt, and that they, who were under it, did not purſue it, in any of its bad Conſequences; but were as careful to live Piouſly, and Vertuouſly, as thoſe could be, who were in the right: Yea, he would ſay, That, for ſome, whom he knew to be ſincere Chriſtians, he thought it was better to let them alone in Innocent Miſtakes; and that there was Danger in going about to ſet them right; yet ſo far as he could fairly do it, he always took care to rectifie Mens Religious Notions, and occaſionally, and by the bye, rather to inſinuate ſome Truths, than purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſet himſelf to Argue, and Defend them.</p>
            <p>His Conduct, among his Pariſhioners, was ſuch, as deſerves Imitation by the whole Order of the Clergy, in their ſeveral Places; and, perhaps, would do more to prevent the growing of Schiſm, than all the Laws that could be contrived in the Church's favour: His buſineſs was to keep up a good Underſtanding betwixt himſelf and his Neighbours, and likewiſe among themſelves. He was ready to ſerve the meaneſt of them, upon all other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, as well as thoſe immediately relating to his Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. If there happened any breach, his Care was to ſtop it in its firſt riſe, well knowing how hard it is, oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to do it afterward. I might here mention ſome Offices of Publick Benefit and Advantage to this Town, which owed themſelves chiefly to his Advice, Induſtry, and Conduct: Particularly, the Settling an Induſtrious and Uſeful School-Maſter among you, and Recovering and Advancing the Credit and Reputation of your Grammar-School. This was his Behaviour among you, and ſuch a mutual Friendſhip was hereby grown up into a Habit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and his Flock, that he would often ſay, If the Governors of the Church ſhould think fit to Reward his hard Labour, with ſome ſmall Dignity in the Church, he would moſt thankfully accept it; but he could never be in a place, where he ſhould be capable of doing more
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51435:16"/>Good, or among a-People, that were more likely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Good from him; and that therefore he could not tell how to entertain any Thoughts of leaving you, as long as he lived. In all the other Relations he bore, which were thoſe a of Father, a Husband, a Son, and a Brother, I never knew any Man that diſcharged theſe Obligations with greater Prudence, or more Exactneſs; with a wiſer Conduct, or a better Senſe of Duty. He had a Capacity which reached almoſt all ſorts of Things, and a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Dexterouſneſs in Diſpatch of Buſineſs; which made him to be ſought to by all the Neighbourhood, and ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to be choſen an Umpire in their Controverſies; in all which, as his Care was to avoid Intrenching upon any other Man's Profeſſion, ſo he never ſought any Advantage to himſelf, but deſigned only doing Good, and obliging Mankind. His Converſation was both Pleaſant and Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. He had, indeed, a ſort of Facetiouſneſs, that was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry natural to him, and perhaps is ſo to moſt Men of free Thoughts; but it was Innocent, and when it had in it any thing of Deſign, it was only to convey wiſe Notices of things in this way, where he knew not how to come at Mens Underſtandings in any other. For my own part, I muſt ſay, that being freed from the neceſſary Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies of a mixt Converſation, I ſcarce ever ſpent an Hour with him, in all the time of our Acquaintance, but with ſome Advantage; and it is a Juſtice due to his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, to own that I have learnt much from him. And, what I take to be a very high Accompliſhment of human Nature, an argument of a great and noble Mind, and not to be omitted in his Character, is, That he was a Wiſe, a Faithful, and an Intire Friend. I had the Happineſs (and a great Happineſs it was to my Life) to live in a perfect Friendſhip with him, which, from our firſt entring into it, (being founded upon no ſelfiſh Ends) never received any interruption; but grew up, and waxed ſtronger, as all good Diſpoſitions do, till they come into confirmed Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits. Whether Friendſhip be diſſolved by Death, on their part, who are gone into another World, I cannot tell. This was one of the Contemplations, our deceaſed Brother
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51435:16"/>was entertaining himſelf with, a little before his Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. He was muſing, as he told me, whether he ſhould be able to do any kind Offices for his Friends, whom he left on Earth: However, on their part, who ſurvive, it is not diſſolved; for there cannot be a more tender Point, than the Name and Memory of a dead Friend. But that which is above all other Endowments, either natural, or acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and which therefore I reſerved to be mentioned in the laſt place, was his lively and vigorous Senſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: He throughly underſtood the Deſign of it, and was very ſenſible of thoſe infinite Obligations we are under, to the Goodneſs of God, for making ſo ample a Proviſion for our Happineſs, as we ſee done, in the Covenant of Grace in Chriſt Jeſus; and for furniſhing us with ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Rules of Life; in the Practice of which Man's Happineſs ſo plainly lies, That our reaches in Vertue give us a very lively Senſe of our future Immortality. He was naturally of a very warm and quick Temper. Thoſe who converſed with him, and knew what a clear and exact Conduct he had of his Mind, may perhaps ſmile at this; as thoſe, who were acquainted with <hi>Socrates,</hi> and knew his abſolute and intire government of his Paſſions, did at the Phyſiognomiſt's Character of him; but that wiſe Man vindicated his Art, and aſſured his Friends, That the Man had judged truly of his natural Temper, which was corrected by the Principles of Philoſophy: And our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Friend would confeſs, That it was not Nature, but Grace that had aſſiſted him in this Work; and that he had done nothing in it, without great Pains firſt taken with himſelf. He was very careful of the Worſhip of God; and as he did all he could to bring his Flock to a ſenſe of Worſhip; being ſirmly perſuaded, that, unleſs Men can be brought to this, That reformation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which is ſo heartily deſired, by all good Men, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be effected; ſo he was very exact in keeping up con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Devotion in his Family, and careful to impreſs a Senſe of it upon his own Children, and thoſe other Youths he was pleaſed to take under his Charge. He was a Man of great Charity, laying aſide, notwithſtanding his large
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51435:17"/>Family, a certain part of his Revenue, annually, for ſuch uſes. Many inſtances of this I have been witneſs to, and ſome of his Charities have paſſed through my Hands, with Directions, not to let the Receivers know who was their Benefactor. He paid for the Teaching of Six poor Boys at your Reading School, and gave as many Bibles Yearly, with the Name of <hi>DEDHAM,</hi> indorſt; which you only underſtood to be a Gift of one, who concealed his Name; but I now acquaint you, That it was intirely his own Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and he has left it, under his Hand, that Five Pounds be paid at your next Governors Feaſt, for Diſcharging the Schooling of theſe Boys, and Furniſhing them with their Bibles, for the Year paſt. He had a mighty Senſe, ſuch a one as is not common, of the Wiſdom of God, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſing of all Events: The Providence of God has been defended admirably well, by many of the Philoſophers: Chriſtianity has helpt us to further Arguments in its De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, by a clear Revelation of a future World, and a Judgment to come; but they are two very different things, to acknowledge a Providence, or plead for it; and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally to comply with it, and to bring our very Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, to conſent to every thing, as beſt, which God does. This latter was what our deceaſed Brother, above all things, aimed at bringing himſelf to. I will give you his Thoughts, in his own words, in a Letter, wrote to me, ſome Months before his laſt Sickneſs. <q>Whether a longer continuance in this World be a Bleſſing, or no, neither you nor I can judge: For my own part, I proteſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly, I have received a Reſignation to the Divine Will as a Principle, from which I will never depart; and I am Labouring for nothing ſo much as to bring my ſelf to approve, in my own Inclinations, the Choices that God ſhall make for me, whatever they be; and this I do, not only becauſe I am ſo perfectly ſatisfied, how much we owe that Obedience to that Government, under which we are; and to the Perfections of that Being, that Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters it; but becauſe I can find no other Principle ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of miniſtring to my Quiet, and of ſupporting my Mind: For, eſpecially as my Thoughts are of my preſent
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51435:17"/>ſtate, if it were not for the force of that, I could never call off my Mind from attending to its apprehenſions of Danger, ſo much, as to do my Duty, and keep the Poſt, the great Diſpoſer of things expects from me, and has placed me in: But with this, notwithſtanding all my ſad Thoughts, I can eat, drink, ſleep, laugh, recreate my ſelf, and enjoy my Friends; and not be uneaſie to them, bleſſed be God, for ſuch Reaſons as we have to leave all Events in his Hand; and to hope they ſhall be merciful to us. For, by this Faith I live, and upon the Stock of this I hope to acquit my ſelf, at leaſt to my own Eternal Safety, when I die.</q> This I take to have been the moſt inward Senſe of his Soul, which abode upon him to the laſt. For, in an interval, not long before his Death, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting him with the hopes his Phyſicians gave us, his Reply was, His Opinion was otherwiſe; and, indeed, ſaid he, now that I am gone on ſo far, unleſs God ſees it beſt to appoint to me a longer Life, I do not think it worth the while to go back. But having exceeded all tolerable Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits allowed to theſe Occaſions, I ſhall only leave with you, that were lately his Charge, the Advice of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Remember them that have the rule over you; or, rather, thoſe that have had the rule over you.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, though it ſignifies any ſort of Ruler, yet, in this place, it muſt be reſtrained to Spiritual Governors, Paſtors, and Teachers; thoſe, who have ſpoken to you the Word of the Lord; and that it muſt refer to them that are dead, I think may be inferred from the latter words, where mention is made of their <hi>exitus,</hi> their departure, or the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Converſation. To remember ſuch a deceaſed Paſtor, is to be thankful to God, that his Providence placed him over you; to be ſenſible of your loſs in being depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of him; to think of him with Love and Affection, and Honour to his Memory; frequently to reflect upon that wiſe Counſel, thoſe wholſome Inſtructions, that Pious Example, which you have often heard from him, and long ſaw in him; and, above all, to continue in that good ſtate, in which he has left you, free from Schiſm in the Church, or Diviſions in your Town; living under a ſenſe of Religion,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51435:18"/>and in Peace and Charity (which has hitherto been your Character) with one another. If you fail in any of theſe Points, beſides that it will upbraid you with unprofitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, under a painful and uſeful Miniſtry long enjoyed; the Effects that will follow, may force you to remember him, but without either Comfort or Advantage to your ſelves; and perhaps to remember alſo my Words to you this Day. But to conclude all with the Words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle; <hi>Beloved,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.4.</note> 
               <hi>we are perſwaded better things of you, and things that accompany Salvation,</hi> I mean, that Promiſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your future Happineſs, than any Miſchief to befal you, <hi>though we thus ſpeak.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:51435:18"/>
            <head>Books Printed for and Sold by <hi>Thomas Speed,</hi> at the <hi>Three Crowns</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil, 1692.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THirty Six Sermons, <hi>viz.</hi> 16 <hi>Ad Aulum.</hi> 6 <hi>Ad Clerum.</hi> 6 <hi>Ad Magiſtratum.</hi> 8 <hi>Ad Populum.</hi> With a large Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, by the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Robert Sanderſon,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi> The Eighth Edition cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and amended. Whereunto is now added the Life of the Reverend and Learned Author. Written by <hi>Iſaac Walton. Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon at the Funeral of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Thomas Grey,</hi> Late Vicar of <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex;</hi> Preach'd in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Dedham, Febr.</hi> the 2d. 1691/2. With a ſhort Account of his Life. By <hi>Joſeph Powell,</hi> A. M. Rector of St. <hi>Mary on the Wall,</hi> in <hi>Colcheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A brief Expoſition of the Church Catechiſm, with Proofs from Scripture. By <hi>John Williams</hi> D. D. Rector of St. <hi>Mildred</hi>'s <hi>Poultrey,</hi> and St. <hi>Mary Cole, London.</hi> The Third Edition. 8o.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tachygraphy;</hi> The moſt Exact and Compendious Method of Short and Swift Writing, that hath ever yet been publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any. Compoſed by <hi>Thomas Shelton,</hi> Author and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of the ſaid Art. Approved by both the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, 8o.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zeiglographia:</hi> Or a New Art of Short writing never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore publiſhed; more Eaſie, Exact, Short, and Speedy than any heretofore. Invented and Compoſed by <hi>Thomas Shelton,</hi> Author and Teacher of the ſaid Art. Allowed by Authority, 8o.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Index Rhetoricus &amp; Oratorius, Scholis, &amp; Inſtitutioni tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioris aetatis accomodatus, cui adjiciuntur formulae Oratoriae, &amp; index Poeticus. Opera &amp; ſtudio Thomae Farnabii. Editio Noviſſima prioribus emendatior,</hi> 12o.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſalmorum Davidis Paraphraſis Poetica Georgii Buchanani Scoti: Argumentis ac Melodiis explicata atque illuſtrata. Opera &amp; Studio Nathanis Chytraei,</hi> 12o.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
